Thousands of years from now,
بعد آلاف السنين من الآن،
we'll look back at the first century of computing
سننظر إلى القرن الأول لبداية استخدام الحواسيب
as a fascinating but very peculiar time --
كمرحلة مدهشة ولكنها غريبة في نفس الوقت--
the only time in history where humans were reduced to live in 2D space,
المرة الأولى في التاريخ التي عاش فيها البشر في عالم ثنائي الأبعاد،
interacting with technology as if we were machines;
حيث يتم التعامل مع التكنولوجيا كأننا آلات،
a singular, 100-year period in the vastness of time
فالفترة الوحيدة التي امتدت 100 عام ضمن الوقت اللانهائي
where humans communicated,
حيث تخاطبت البشرية مع بعضها البعض،
were entertained and managed their lives
واستمتعوا بالترفيه،وسيروا حياتهم
from behind a screen.
من خلف شاشة.
Today, we spend most of our time tapping and looking at screens.
ونحن نقضي اليوم أغلب أوقاتنا ونحن نضغط أو ننظر إلى شاشات
What happened to interacting with each other?
ماذا حدث لتفاعلنا مع بعضنا البعض؟
I don't know about you, but I feel limited
لست متأكداً من رأيكم، ولكنني أشعر أنني محصور
inside this 2D world of monitors and pixels.
داخل عالم ثنائي الأبعاد من الشاشات والبكسلات.
And it is this very limitation
وهذا الحصار بالتحديد
and my desire to connect with people
ورغبتي في التواصل مع الناس
that inspires me as a creator.
هو الدافع وراء إلهامي كمخترع.
Put simply: I want to create a new reality,
ببساطة: أرغب في إيجاد واقع جديد،
a reality where technology brings us infinitely closer to each other,
واقع تتمكن التكنولوجيا به من جعلنا أقرب لبعضنا البعض.
a reality where people, not devices,
واقع يكون به الإنسان وليس الآلة
are the center of everything.
هو محور كل شيء.
I dream of a reality where technology senses what we see, touch and feel;
إنني أحلم بواقع تتمكن التكنولوجيا به من الإحساس بما نراه ونلمس ونشعر
a reality where technology no longer gets in our way,
واقع لا تكون فيه التكنولوجيا عائقاً
but instead embraces who we are.
بل تتقبل ما نحن عليه.
I dream of technology
أحلم بتقنية
on a human path.
تكون خطوة في طريق الإنسانية.
We have all experienced technology
جميعنا تعاملنا مع التقنية
that enables people to act more like people,
التي تمكن الناس من أن يتصرفوا بحرية وعلى طبيعتهم،
products that enable natural interactions, voice controls or biometrics.
مع منتجات تقوي من التفاعلات الطبيعية، التحكم الصوتي أو القياسات الحيوية.
This is the next step in the evolution.
هذه هي الخطوة التالية في التطور.
This is Microsoft HoloLens,
هذه "هولولينس" من مايكروسوفت،
the first fully untethered holographic computer.
أول كمبيوتر للمجسمات الثلاثية الأبعاد مستقل بذاته.
Devices like this will bring 3D holographic content
أجهزة كهذه قادرة أن تشكل مجسمات ثلاثية الأبعاد
right into our world,
في عالمنا اليوم.
enhancing the way we experience life
معززة بذلك طريقة تعاملنا مع الحياة
beyond our ordinary range of perceptions.
بشكل أبعد من وسائل الإدراك الحالية.
Now, I'm not thinking about a distant future.
حسناً،أنا لا أتكلم عن المستقبل البعيد
I'm talking about today.
أنا أتحدث عن اليوم.
We are already seeing car companies like Volvo
يوجد الآن شركات سيارات مثل "فولفو"
designing cars differently with HoloLens;
تقوم بتصميم سياراتها بطريقة مختلفة باستخدام "هولولينس،"
universities like Case Western redefining the way medical students learn;
جامعات مثل "كايس ويسترن" تعيد طريقة تقديم تعليم الطب لطلابها،
and my personal favorite,
والمثال المفضل لدي،
NASA is using HoloLens to let scientists explore planets
تستخدم ناسا "هولولينس" لتتيح لعلمائها اكتشاف الكواكب
holographically.
بطريثة ثلاثية الأبعاد.
Now, this is important.
هذا أمر هام فعلاً.
By bringing holograms into our world,
باستخدام الصور المجسمة في حياتنا اليومية
I'm not just talking about a new device or a better computer.
لا أتحدث عن أجهزة جديدة أو جهاز كمبيوتر أفضل.
I'm talking about freeing ourselves from the 2D confines
ولكني أتحدث عن تحرير أنفسنا من حدود العالم ثثنائي الأبعاد
of traditional computing.
الموجودة في أجهزة الحواسيب التقليدية.
Put it this way:
لننظر للأمر من هذه الزاوية:
temporally adjusted, we're like cave people in computer terms.
مع تعديل للزمان، نحن كإنسان الكهف في تعاملنا مع الكمبيوتر.
We've barely discovered charcoal
فقد اكتشفنا الآن الفحم النباتي
and started drawing the first stick figures in our cave.
وبدأنا في رسم الرسوم البسيطة على جدران الكهف.
Now, this is the perspective I apply to my work every single day.
هذه هي النظرة التي أطبقها أثناء عملي اليومي.
And now for the next few minutes,
والآن خلال الدقائق القادمة،
I invite all of you to apply the same perspective
أدعوكم لتطبيق نفس النظرة
to the journey ahead of us.
أثناء قيامنا بالرحلة التالية.
Now, as I put this HoloLens on,
الآن أقوم بوضع "هولولنس" وتشغيلها،
let me explain the setup a little bit.
دعوني أشرح الإعدادات لكم قليلاً.
It's probably the most risky demo we have ever done on any stage
وهذا لربما كان أخطر عرض قمنا به على أي منصة
with HoloLens,
باستخدام "هولولنس،"
and I can't think of a better place to do it than here at TED.
ولا يمكنني أن أفكر في مكان أفضل للقيام بذلك من مسرح TED.
Momentarily, I am going to be seeing holograms
خلال لحظات سأبدأ في مشاهدة رسومات مجسمة
right on this stage,
هنا على هذه المنصة،
just as clearly as I can see all of you.
بشكل واضح كما يمكنني رؤيتكم الآن.
Now at the same time, we have also this special camera
في نفس الوقت، توجد لدينا كاميرا خاصة
that just walked in onstage
والتي دخلت لمسرحنا الآن.
so that all of you can share in this experience with me
لكي تتمكنوا جميعا من مشاركة التجربة معي
up on all the monitors.
من خلال شاشات العرض.
So let's start our journey.
فلنبدأ رحلتنا.
And what better place to begin our journey,
وليس هناك من مكان أفضل لنبدأ به
than in the computer cave of 2D.
من كهف أجهزتنا الحالية ثنائي الأبعاد.
Let's explore the world all around us with this new lens,
لنقم باكتشاف العالم حولنا باستخدام هذه العدسات الجديدة،
and understand the computer world from a brand new perspective.
ونفهم عالم الكمبيوتر من خلال نظرة جديدة كلياً.
The computer universe is both marvelous and primitive.
إن عالم الكمبيوتر هو شيء رائع وبدائي على حد سواء.
It's a universe based on causality.
فهو عالم مبني على السببية.
As developers, we dream the different causes
كمطورين، نقوم بتخيل عدة مسببات
and then we program the different effects.
ومن ثم نقوم ببرمجة النتائج المختلفة.
Double click on an icon, that's a cause.
الضغط مرتين على رمز هو سبب.
Open an application, that's an effect.
وإطلاق تطبيق ما، هو النتيجة.
Now when we compare this to our physical universe,
وحين نقوم بمقارنة ذلك مع عالمنا المحسوس،
it is overly constraining,
فيسنجده مقيدا جدا،
because our universe is not digital.
لأن كوننا ليس رقميا.
Our universe is analog.
بل هو كون تناظري.
Our universe doesn't think in terms of zero or one,
عالمنا لا يعمل على مبدإ الرقمين الواحد والصفر،
true or false, or black or white.
الصح والخطأ، أو الأبيض والأسود.
We exist in a world governed by quantum physics,
نحن نعيش في عالم يعمل طبقاً لفيزياء الكم،
a universe of zero and one both at the same time,
كون يجمع الواحد والصفر معا في نفس الوقت،
a reality based on infinite probabilities and shades of gray.
واقع يعتمد على احتمالات لا نهائية وظلال رمادية.
You can see how these two worlds collide.
يمكنكم أن تروا كيف يتصادم هذان العالمان معاً.
So why are screens so pervasive in our analog life?
إذن لماذا تنتشر الشاشات في عالمنا التناظري؟
We see screens from the moment we wake up,
نحن نشاهد الشاشات منذ لحظة استيقاظنا
to the moment we fall asleep.
وإلى اللحظة التي نخلد للنوم.
Why?
لماذا؟
I think it's because computers give us superpowers.
أعتقد السبب هو أن أجهزة الكمبيوتر تعطينا قدرات خارقة.
Within the digital universe, we have the power to displace space
ففي العالم الرقمي نملك القدرة على تغيير المكان
and the power to displace time.
والقدرة على تغيير الزمان.
It doesn't matter if you're using technology for entertainment,
ليس مهماً إن كنت تستخدم التكنولوجيا للترفيه
productivity or communication.
للإنتاجية أو الاتصالات.
Think of it this way:
لنفكر بهذه الطريقة:
let's all go home tonight
لنذهب جميعا لمنازلنا الليلة
and watch our favorite show on television.
ونشاهد برنامجنا المفضل على التلفاز.
This is theater -- time and space displaced.
في هذا المسرح، يمكننا تغير الزمان والمكان
As soon as I'm done with this TED Talk,
فور انتهائي من حديثي هذا في TED،
I'm going to immediately call my lovely family in Seattle.
سأتصل فوراً بعائلتي الجميلة في سياتل.
That's displacement of space.
هذا تغبير للمكان.
Now, these are such great superpowers
هذه قوى خارقة هامة
that we put up with the two-dimensional limitations
نتعايش معها في حدودنا ثنائية الأبعاد
of our current digital world.
لعالمنا الرقمي الحالي.
But what if we didn't have to?
لكن ماذا إن لم نكن مضطرين لذلك؟
What if we could have these same digital powers
ماذا إن كنا قادرين على أن نحصل على نفس القوى الرقمية
in our world?
في عالمنا نحن؟
You can already see glimmers of this,
يمكننا أن نشاهد لمحات من هذا،
but I believe our children's children
ولكنني مقتنع أن أولاد أولادنا
will grow up in a world devoid of 2D technology.
سيكبرون في عالم يخلومن التقنية ثنائية الأبعاد.
It's remarkable to dream of this world,
من المهم أن نحلم بهذا العالم
a world where technology truly understands us --
عالم حيث يمكن للتكنولوجيا أن تفهمنا حقاً--
where we live, work and communicate --
حيث نعيش، ونعمل ونتواصل--
with tools that enhance the human experience,
مستخدمين أدوات تعمل على تعزيز التجربة الإنسانية،
not machines that limit our humanity.
وليس آلات تعمل على الحد من إنسانيتنا.
So how do we get there?
إذن كيف نصل إلى هناك؟
For me, the answer required looking at the problem
بالنسبة لي، الأمر يتطلب النظر للمشكلة
from a different perspective.
من منظور مختلف.
It required sensing the world from the perspective of a machine.
منظور يتطلب أن نرى العالم من وجهة نظر الآلة.
If you're a machine trying to sense our world,
إن كنت آلة تحاول أن تفهم عالمنا،
how would you actually break the problem down?
فكيف ستقوم بتحليل الأمر وتجزئته لكي تفهمه؟
You'd probably try to classify things
ربما ستقوم بتصنيف الأشياء من حولك
as a human,
كإنسان،
an environment
أو بيئة
or an object.
أو كجماد.
But how would that machine then interact with reality?
لكن كيف ستصبح الآلة قادرة على التفاعل مع الواقع؟
And I can think of three ways.
يمكنني أن أفكر بثلاثة طرق.
First, as a machine,
أولاً، كآلة،
I would observe or I would input reality.
سأراقب وأستوعب الواقع.
Speech recognition and biometric authentication
التعرف الصوتي والتوثيق الحيوي
are great examples of a machine interacting with humans
هما مثالان مهمان لكيفية تعامل الآلة مع الإنسان
from an input perspective.
من زاوية نظر المعلومات المزودة.
Secondly, as a machine,
ثانياً٫ كآلة،
I could place digital information, or output information,
يمكنني أن أعكس المعلومات الرقمية أو المعلومات الناتجة،
into reality.
على أرض الواقع.
Holograms are examples of a machine interacting with an environment
الرسوم المجسمة هي مثال عن آلة تتفاعل مع الواقع
from an output perspective.
من وجهة نظر المعلومات الناتجة.
Finally, as a machine,
أخيرا، كآلة،
I could exchange energy with the world via haptics.
يمكنني أن أتبادل الطاقة مع العالم المحيط باللمس.
Now, imagine being able to feel the temperature of a virtual object,
تخيل أن تكون قادراً أن تشعر بحرارة جسم افتراضي،
or better yet, imagine pushing a hologram
أو الأفضل من ذلك، تخيل أن تستطيع دفع رسم مجسم
and having it push you back with equal force.
ويقوم الرسم بدفعك أيضا بقوة مماثلة.
With this perspective,
من خلال وجهة النظر هذه،
we are able to collapse reality into a simple matrix.
يمكننا أن نختصر الواقع إلى مصفوفة بسيطة.
Now here's a secret:
سأخبركم بسر:
as an engineer, I get really excited
كمهندس، يحمسني أي شيء في الواقع
anytime I can reduce something to the matrix.
يمكنني أن أختصره ليكون مصفوفة.
From self-driving cars
بدأ من السيارات ذاتية القيادة
to smartphones
إلى الهواتف الذكية
to this holographic computer on my head,
إلى الكمبيوترلثلاثي الأبعاد الذي على رأسي.
machines are becoming capable of understanding our world.
أصبحت الآلات قادرة على أن تفهم عالمنا.
And they are starting to interact with us
وقد بدأت تتفاعل معنا
in significantly more personal ways.
بطرق أكثر شخصية.
Now, imagine having granular control
تخيل الآن وجود تحكم دقيق
over everything in the world.
بكل شيء موجود في العالم.
Move the dial one way,
أدر قرص التحكم في اتجاه،
and you get reality.
وستحصل على الواقع.
Move the dial the other way,
أدر قرص التحكم بالاتجاه الآخر،
and you get virtual reality.
وستحصل على الواقع الافتراضي.
Now, imagine dialing your entire environment
تخيل أن تضبط عالمك المحيط بك
between virtual and real worlds.
ليكون وسطاً بين الواقع والواقع الافتراضي
I love it down here.
أحب هذا المكان.
Now, imagine if I could look at all of you
الآن تخيلوا أنني أنظر إليكم جميعاً
and dial from real humans into elves.
وأحول كل إنسان أراه ليصبح جنيا صغيرا.
When technology truly understands our world,
حين تفهم التقنية عالمنا حقاً،
it will again transform the ways we interact,
فإنها ستغير الطريقة التي نتفاعل بها،
the ways we work and the ways we play.
والطريقة التي نعمل ونلعب بها.
Less than half a century ago,
قبل أقل من نصف قرن،
two courageous men landed on the moon,
هبط رجلان شجاعان على القمر،
using computers that were less powerful than the phones in your pockets.
مستخدمين جهاز كمبيوتر أقل قوة من أجهزة الهاتف الجوال في جيوبنا.
Six hundred million humans watched them
وشاهدهم 600 مليون شخص
on grainy, black-and-white televisions.
على شاشات أجهزة التلفاز القديمة البيضاء والسوداء.
And the world?
كيف كان حال العالم؟
The world was mesmerized.
كان العالم مفتوناً.
Now imagine how our children and their children
تخيل الآن كيف سيقوم أولادنا وأولاد أولادنا
will experience the continued exploration of space
باختبار استكشاف الفضاء المستمر
with technology that understands this world.
مستخدمين تكنولوجيا قادرة على فهم هذا العالم.
We already live in a world where real-time universal translators exist.
نحن نعيش في عالم يوجد به مترجمون عالميون فوريون.
And I can squint, and I can already see holographic telepresence
ويمكنني أن أغلق عيني قليلا وأرى أجهزة نقل صور ذاتية ثلاثية الأبعاد
in our near future.
في مستقبلنا القريب.
In fact, since we've been lucky with our demo so far,
في الواقع، وحيث أننا كنا محظوظين في عرضنا إلى الآن،
let's try doing something else even more crazy.
لنحاول القيام بشيء أكثر جنوناً.
I invite you to experience,
أدعوكم لخوض تجربة،
for the first time anywhere in the world,
لأول مرة في أي مكان في العالم،
here on the TED stage,
هنا على مسرح TED
a real-life holographic teleportation,
تجربة حية لجهاز انتقال آني ثلاثي الأبعاد،
between me and my friend, Dr. Jeffrey Norris,
بيني وبين صديقي الدكتور "جيفري نوريس،"
from NASA's Jet Propulsion Laboratory.
من مختبر الدفع النفاث في ناسا.
Finger crossed. Hi, Jeff.
لنأمل أن تعمل، مرحباً "جيف."
Jeff Norris: Hey, Alex.
جيفنونوريس: مرحباً أليكس.
Alex Kipman: Phew! That worked. How are you doing today, Jeff?
أليكسكيبمان: لقد نجحت التجربة، كيف حالك "جيف"؟
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
JN: Doing great. I had an awesome week.
ج.ن: أنا بخير، قضيت أسبوعاً رائعاً.
AK: So, can you tell us a little bit, Jeff, about where you are?
أ.ك: أيمكنك أن تخبرنا بمكانك يا جيف؟
JN: Well, I'm actually in three places.
ج.ن: أنا في الحقيقة في ثلاثة أماكن مختلفة.
I'm standing in a room across the street,
أنا أقف في غرفة على الجانب الآخر من الشارع،
while I'm standing on this stage with you,
بينما أقف على المنصة معك،
while I'm standing on Mars, a hundred million miles away.
بينما أقف على سطح المريخ على بعد مئات الملاين من الأميال.
AK: Wow, a hundred million miles away. This is crazy!
أ.ك: مئات الملاين من الأميال! هذا جنون.
Can you tell us a little bit more about where all this data
أيمكنك أن تخبرنا قليلاً من أين تأتي البينات الخاصة
from Mars is coming from?
بالمريخ؟
JN: Absolutely.
ج.ن: بالطبع.
This is a precise holographic replica of Mars,
هذه رسوم ثلاثية الأبعاد للمريخ دقيقة جداً،
built from data captured by the Curiosity Mars Rover,
تم بناؤها من البينات التي جمعتها العربة "كيريوسيتي" على المريخ،
that I can explore as easily as a place on Earth.
ويمكنني استكشاف المكان بكل سهولة كأنه موجود على الأرض.
Humans are natural explorers.
البشر هم مستكشفون بطبيعتهم.
We can instantly understand an environment,
يمكننا أن نفهم بيئة ما مباشرة،
just by being present in it.
فقط من خلال تواجدنا بها.
We've built tools like our Mars Rover
لقد بنينا أدوات كمارس روفر
to extend our vision and lengthen our reach.
لكي نوسع نظرنا ونمدد مدى وصولنا.
But for decades,
لكن لعقود عدة،
we've explored from a seat behind screens and keyboards.
كنا نستكشف ونحن جلوس خلف شاشات ولوحات المفاتيح.
Now, we're leaping over all of that,
والآن، نحن نقفز فوق هذا كله،
over the giant antennas and the relay satellites
فوق الهوائيات العملاقة والأقمار الصناعية لتقوية الإرسال
and the vastness between worlds
والمساحات الشاسعة بين العوالم
to take our first steps on this landscape as if we were truly there.
لنقوم بخطوتنا الأولى في هذا العالم وكأننا هناك حقاً.
Today, a group of scientists on our mission
وتقوم مجموعة من الباحثين في مهمتنا
are seeing Mars as never before --
بمشاهدة المريخ كما لم يفعلوا من قبل--
an alien world made a little more familiar,
عالم غريب أصبح مألوفاً أكثر،
because they're finally exploring it as humans should.
لأننا نقوم باستكشافه كما يجب أن يفعل البشر.
But our dreams don't have to end with making it just like being there.
لكن أحلامنا لا يجب آن تنتهي بمجرد أننا قدرنا على تصور وجودنا هناك.
When we dial this real world to the virtual,
عندما نجعل هذا العالم افتراضيا،
we can do magical things.
يمكننا القيام بأمور أشبه بالسحر.
We can see in invisible wavelengths
يمكننا أن نرى عبر موجات غير مرئية
or teleport to the top of a mountain.
أو ننتقل آنياً لقمة جبل.
Perhaps someday, we'll feel the minerals in a rock just by touching it.
لربما في يوم ما نتمكن من تحسس المعادن في صخرة ما باللمس.
We're taking the first steps.
نحن نخطو خطواتنا الأولى.
But we want the whole world to join us in taking the next,
ولكننا نرغب أن يشاركنا العالم أجمع في هذه الخطوات،
because this is not a journey for a few,
لأن هذه الرحلة لا تعني أشخاصا معينين فقط،
but for all of us.
ولكنها تعينينا جميعاً.
AK: Thank you Jeff, this was amazing.
أ.ك: شكرا يا "جيف"، لقد كان هذا رائعاً.
Thank you so much for joining us on the TED stage today.
شكراً جزيلاً لانضمامك معنا على منصة TED اليوم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
JN: Thank you Alex, bye bye.
ج.ن: شكرا لك "أليكس"، إلى اللقاء.
AK: Bye, Jeff.
أليكس: إلى اللقاء "جيف."
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
I dream about this future
أحلم بهذا المستقبل
every single day.
كل يوم.
I take inspiration from our ancestors.
أستمد إلهامي من أسلافنا.
We used to live in tribes where we interacted,
كنا نعيش في قبائل حيث كنا نتعامل،
communicated and worked together.
ونتواصل ونعمل معاً.
We are all beginning to build technology that will enable us to return
نعمل جميعا على بناء تقنية تسمح لنا أن نعود
to the humanity that brought us where we are today --
إلى إنسانيتنا التي أوصلتنا إلى ما نحن عليه اليوم--
technology that will let us stop living inside this 2D world
تقنية تخرجنا من حدود العيش داخل العالم ثنائي الأبعاد
of monitors and pixels,
في الشاشات والبيكسل،
and let us start remembering what it feels like
ولنتذكر معاً ما هو إحساس
to live in our 3D world.
أن تعيش في عالم ثلاثي الأبعاد.
It's a phenomenal time to be human.
إن هذا وقت استثنائي لنكون هنا كبشر.
Thank you.
شكرا جزيلا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Helen Walters: Thanks so much. I have some questions.
هيلين والترز: شكراً جزيلاً، لدي بعض الأسئلة.
AK: OK.
أليكس: حسنا.
HW: So there's been some talk in the press.
ه.و: تواردت أحاديث في الصحف.
And I'll just ask you straight, then we have a straight answer.
وسأسلك سؤالا مباشرا، لكي نحصل على جواب مباشر.
There's been talk about the difference between the demos
تواردت أحاديث عن فروقات بين استعراض هذه التقنية
and the reality of the commercial product.
وما تقدمه المنتجات التجارية الواقعية.
Talk about this field of view issue.
لنتحدث عن هذا الجانب من رأي الناس.
Is this type of experience what someone who buys the product will get?
هل سيحصل من يشتري هذه التقنية على نفس التجربة التي شهدناها؟
AK: It's a great question,
أ.ك: إنه سؤال مهم.
Or, said better, this is a question we've been receiving
في الحقيقة، هذا هو السؤال الذي كان يصلنا
in the media for possibly the last year.
من وسائل الإعلام لمدة تقارب العام.
If you do your research, I haven't answered that question.
إن قمت بالبحث، فأنا لم أقدم إجابة على هذا السؤال
I've purposely ignored it,
لقد قمت بتجاهله قصداً،
because ultimately, it's the wrong question to ask.
لأن في نهاية المطاف، هذا السؤال الخطأ.
That's the equivalent of me showing holograms to someone for the first time,
هذا مشابه لأن أقوم بعرض المجسمات ثلاثية الأبعاد لشخص ما لأول مرة،
and you then saying, "What's the size of your television?"
ومن ثم تسألينني "ما هو حجم جهاز التلفاز لديك؟"
The field of view for the product is almost irrelevant.
وجهة النظر لهذا المنتج هي غير هامة تقريبا.
What we should be talking about is the density of lights,
ما يجب أن نناقشه هو ما هي كثافة الضوء،
or radiance, that shows up.
أو الإشعاع،هو الذي ظهر.
Better said, what the angular resolution is of the things that you see.
أو ما هي دقة الزاوية التي من خلالها ترى الأشياء.
So from that perspective, what you saw --
من وجهة النظر هذه، ما تراه--
you know, the camera is wearing a HoloLens.
أتعلمين،أن الكاميرا ترتدي الهولولينس.
So even if I wanted to cheat, I can't.
بالتالي حتى إن رغبت أن أغش، فلن أستطيع.
HW: But the camera has a different lens on it than our eye. Right?
ه.و: لكن للكاميرا عدسة مختلفة عما يوجد في أعيننا، صحيح؟
AK: The camera has a fish-eye lens on it.
أ.ك: لدى الكاميرا عدسة عين السمكة.
It's seeing a much wider view than the human eye is.
وهي ترى زاوية أوسع من قدرة العين البشرية.
So if you think about the points of light that show up radially
لذا إن كنت تفكرين في النقاط المضيئة التي تشع
from the vision of the camera,
من وجهة نظر الكاميرا،
which is the thing that matters:
وهو الأمر المهم:
how many points of light can I get in a given volume?
ما عدد نقاط الضوء التي يمكن الحصول عليها في حجم معين؟
That's the same as I get on this HoloLens as I will on that one.
سيكون العدد الذي أحصل عليه من "هولولينس" مشابها لما أحصل عليه من تلك.
Now, this camera sees a much wider view of the world, right?
الآن، تلك الكاميرا قادرة على رؤية زاوية أوسع، صحيح؟
HW: Jesus Christ!
هيلين: يا إلهي!
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
AK: He did show up! I told you he'd show up.
أ.ك: لقد ظهر، أخبرتك أنه سيظهر.
Come this way.
تعالي إلى هنا.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
HW: Oh, shit.
ه.و: يا للهول.
AK: And there's holographic Jeff Norris.
أ.ك: هذا جيف نوريس كصورة ثلاثية الأبعاد.
HW: I knew something was happening, but I really wasn't sure what.
ه.و: كنت أعلم أن هناك شيء ما يحدث، لكن لم أكن متأكدة ماهو.
AK: So in short: to be super crisp,
أ.ك: باختصار ولأكون واضحا جداً،
the camera that you see on the screen has a wider field of view
الكاميرا التي ترينها على الشاشة تمتلك مجال رؤية أكبر
than the human eye.
مقارنة بالعين البشرية.
But the angular resolution of the holograms that you see,
لكن دقة الزاوية للصور المجسمة التي ترينها،
the points of light per unit of area,
نقاط الضوء لكل وحدة في منطقة ما،
are actually the same.
هي في الواقع متطابقة.
HW: So you spent -- Jeff, I'll get to you in a minute --
ه.و: لقد قضيت-- جيف،سأتكلم معك عما قليل--
so you spent a lot of time mapping the stage --
لقد قضيت وقتا طويلا وأنت تأخذ مقاسات المنصة--
AK: That's right.
أ.ك: هذا صحيح.
HW: So help me out here:
ه.و: إذا ساعدني قليلاً:
if I buy a HoloLens and have it at home,
إن اشتريت "هولولينس" واستخدمتها في المنزل،
I don't need to map my apartment, right?
لن أحتاج لأخذ مقاسات شقتي أليس كذلك؟
AK: The HoloLens maps in real time at about five frames per second,
أ.ك: تأخذ "هولولينس" المقاسات وهي تعمل، ما يقارب خمسة إطارات في الثانية،
with this technology that we call spatial mapping.
باستخدام هذه التقنية التي نسميها رسم الخرائط الحيزي.
So in your home, as soon as you put it on,
لذا بمجرد أن ترتديها في المنزل،
holograms will start showing up, and you'll start placing them
ستبدأ الرسوم المجسمة بالظهور وستستطيعين تحريكها
and they'll start learning your home.
وستبدأ في التأقلم مع منزلك.
In a stage environment where we're trying to get something on my head
أما على المنصة حيث نحاول أن نضع شيئا على رأسي
to communicate with something over there
وأتواصل مع شخص آخر بعيد عني
with all of the wireless connectivity that usually brings all conferences down,
ومشاكل الاتصالات اللاسلكية التي يمكن أن تعطل المؤتمرات،
we don't take the risk of trying to do this live.
فنحن لا نخاطر بتجربة هذا الأمر على الهواء مباشرة.
So what we do is pre-map the stage at five frames per second
لذلك نقوم بأخذ مقاسات المنصة بسرعة خمسة إطارات في الثانية
with the same spatial-mapping technology
مستخدمين تقنية رسم الخرائط الحيزي ذاتها
that you'll use with the product at home,
التي ستسخدمينها مع المنتج في المنزل،
and then we store it,
ونخزن تلك المقاسات،
so that when there's shenanigans of wireless in an environment like this,
لنستخدمها في حال حدوث أي خلل في الاتصال اللاسلكي في بيئة كهذه،
between the camera's HoloLens and the one on my head,
ما بين الكاميرا التي تستعمل "هولولينس" والتي أرتديها،
we don't have things disappear.
فإن الأشياء لن تختفي.
Because ultimately, the holograms are coming from this HoloLens,
لأن في النهاية، الرسوم المجسمة تأتي من "هولولينس" هذه،
and that one is just viewing the HoloLens.
وتلك تعكس ما تراه "هولولينس" .
So if I lose connectivity,
لذا إن فقدت الاتصال بينهما،
you would stop seeing beautiful things on the screen.
فستفقدون رؤية تلك الأشياء الجميلة على الشاشة.
HW: And it was beautiful.
ه.و: لقد كانت جميلة.
Um ... Jeff?
امم... "جيف"؟
JN: Yes?
ج.ن: نعم؟
HW: Hi.
ه.و: مرحباً.
AK: I'll take a step back.
أ.ك: سأرجع للخلف خطوة.
HW: So Jeff, you were on Mars,
ه.و: جيف، لقد كنت على سطح المريخ،
you were here, you were in a room across the street.
كما كنت هنا،وكنت أيضا على الناحية الأخرى من الشارع.
Tell me more about the fact that, with holograms, you have sight
أخبرني أكثر عن قدرة الرسوم المجسمة أن تعطيك الرؤية
but you don't have touch, you don't have smell.
ولكن لا يمكن أن تعطيك قدرة اللمس أو الشم.
Is this scientifically useful now?
هل هذا مفيد علميا الآن؟
That's my question for a hologram.
هذا سؤالي لصورة مجسمة.
JN: Thanks for the question.
ج.ن: أشكرك على السؤال.
Absolutely, I believe that these technologies
بالقطع، لدي قناعة تامة أن هذه التقنيات
are scientifically useful right now,
لديها فائدة علمية حاليا،
and that's why we're using them in multiple parts of our work at NASA.
ولهذا السبب نحن نستخدمها حاليا في جوانب مختلفة في عملنا لدى ناسا.
So we're using it to improve the ways that we explore Mars.
نستخدمها لنحسن من الطرق التي نستكشف بها المريخ.
We're also using it for our astronauts on the space station.
كما تستخدم من قبل رواد الفضاء على متن المحطة الفضائية الدولية.
We're even using it now to design
كما نستخدمها أيضا لتصميم
the next generation of our spacecraft.
الجيل المقبل من سفن الفضاء.
HW: Amazing. OK, Jeff, please go away. Thank you very much.
ه.و: رائع،حسنا،جيف. أرجوك أن تذهب الآن، شكراً جزيلاً.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Alex, really, that was amazing. Thank you so much.
أليكس،صدقا، ، كان هذا رائعاً ،شكرا جزيلاً.
AK: Thank you.
أ.ك: شكرا جزيلا.
HW: Thank you. Thank you.
ه.و: شكرا، شكرا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)